First uh I I give a quick quick intro
from the re research perspective. Um and
this is actually my my second time at
Berkeley. Uh the first time I I talked
about this kind of things learning uh
learning from human feedback using a
technique called marginal likelihood
which was actually developed here uh via
my PhD advisor Percy. Um it's actually
an alternative to RL but uh with all the
emphasis on exploration and also because
of the log you have to do well on every
single example. Um yeah anyways we try
that but without uh without
pre-training.
Um more more recently oh
yeah so um more more recently I was uh
very very interested in code LMS. I
thought uh okay yeah they seem to be
really uh really impressive maybe a
really good way to get to uh better
better AI kind of following
um you know previously it was still
language to programs now it's a code LMS
um did a bunch of work on that um and
we're responsible for um or partly
responsible for a bunch of benchmarks in
the space um and mo most recently I
worked on a gantic RL on this uh code uh
world model project that's recently
released
um okay but today I really want to talk
about these uh benchmarks
uh so you know when when you create um
and actually if I I'm correct this this
class had quite a few um uh lectures
about benchmark you in intro to
benchmark already so so I won't cover
specific benchmarks
Um and you know when you when you make
these uh benchmarks it's all quite quite
busy. There's considerations about uh oh
is this going to be effective um what's
the quality right there there's very
very little um
reflection
on them. So so this is what what uh I
want to talk about today. Um okay so you
know back then you do you do a bit
better 10% better on image net it's a
huge data set um then there is no no
doubt that this uh this is this works
uh what's happening now is that u we
have these more complex agentic
benchmark well I mean Q evol is no
longer a complex benchmark but it was a
generative benchmark that takes a while
to make and evaluate
Um and many uh many paper report a
relatively small improvement on them.
And if you look at the traditional
standard of statistical significance,
many of the improvements are certainly
not significant,
right? And if you look at the sizes
actually uh benchmarks are kind of
getting harder but smaller, right? So um
Amnest was 10,000 imageet 100,000 before
really real generative benchmarks the
multiple choice ones like MLU uh 10,000
but once we got to these coding
benchmarks they go down to like human
evolve which is one of the landmark
benchmark in the area only 164 examples
uh others a little bit bigger you know I
feel that I I was responsible partially
responsible for Crocol DS 1000. We will
try to allow live code benching. We will
try to shoot for about a thousand but
still quite a bit smaller than before.
Um
and now there are these even more
complex agency evolves such as SW banch
uh various versions terminal bench uh
which often needs uh hundred of
thousands of tokens and often ours
depends on how how you run them. So
these are tend to be also in the in the
hundreds.
Okay. So um one counterpoint then is um
you know each question now can be quite
uh quite powerful and and informative
right so because you generate a lot of
uh text or code or these agentic
trajectories when you when you solve
these problems
um and that feels like it should be
better than say uh true true and false
or multiple choice or classification
questions Right. And I think we also
have a certain intuition from humans
from all your experience being a
student. Uh right. So so leading leading
I I guess intellectual contests have
very few questions but long very long
answers. So so for for instance
um u not sure. Yeah. But IMO which the
math Olympi has six questions. The
college version has 12 questions.
Yeah. And they they have a range range
of difficulties.
Okay. And uh I think it's also in in the
era now that if you if you solve a major
open problem, you just have to uh you
just have to solve one, right? And no
one is going to say, oh, you you only
solved one problem. That's not
statistically significant. And there are
many the uh of the more daily agentic
tasks which are more more economically
important such as fixing issues, find
bugs, wipe code and I'm sure many many
in other domains.
Um okay. Yeah. So so here I pose a
question. Uh so what's the case? Um are
small benchmarks not reliable even if
they contain these hard complex
questions or B uh can we somehow
um get more out of uh these complex
questions and we we in fact should use
these small but very hard benchmarks.
Now there are lots of uh benchmarks,
lots of uh leaderboards, right? Some of
these leaderboards really tell tell you
uh exactly what the model did on each
question.
Um and otherwise you can you can also
run some kind of evaluation suite and uh
um get get the individual individual
performance.
So uh in in this attempt at exploratory
data analysis um I have each each dot on
this plot is a is a question and and a
model actually each uh each column
represents a model and each row
represents a question and they are
doubly sorted. So so the models are
placed at uh how how well they do on
average on that benchmark. That's that's
the x-axxis. We have the models on the
see the cursor. Yeah. Okay. Um
you have the models on the left uh being
the best models and the model on the
right being the worst models and the
questions are uh just uh sorted from
from the easiest question to to the to
the hardest question. So the y axis is
its rank and the color is u uh the
accuracy of that model on this question.
Um okay.
>> Yeah. So so we have have this kind of
data. Uh you see uh there there seems to
be a clear clear trend of easy questions
and hard questions, right? Good models
and bad models and uh you know a
somewhat sharp transition
right um from from uh from from this uh
plot right. So this was on math 500
chain of thought.
All right. And we can we can look at
many many benchmarks. I try to get a lot
of the a lot of it where where there's
data available or um or I can I can run
them. Uh so some some are a bit noisy.
So then we have human evol.
Um right the the maybe the division on
human evil is less clear but still clear
on uh BPP uh some sometimes you cannot
get right so the color gradient is
because we have multiple draws for for
each question
um right where where you know yellow is
like a 0.5%
probability of getting correct on a
question
but sometimes These are external
benchmarks that's aggregated by by other
people and then we just get a binary uh
practice suggestion. So, so bunch
leaderboard is one of the more most
comprehensive with with more than 100
model plus agent participating
um and uh and the live code on the on
the right is another um I think yeah
lead the lead lead author now it's also
from Berkeley. Um
yeah so so even even though they're they
are binary you can you can still see
there are easy easy problems hard
problems and uh some some some problems
where no models solve
okay so one one thing I can observe is
there's just from this exploratory data
analysis there there's a lot of
inconsistency
Right? So even though the model the
model on the left is the best, right?
But sometimes it fails on a on an easy
problem
and uh uh and some of the really rather
bad models that succeed um only maybe 20
30 something% of the time or but they
they succeed on some pretty hard
problems.
Um so so this suggests to me that maybe
the problems in the in these benchmarks
are not that special and uh even bad
models have a chance of getting them
correctly um even though maybe a lower
chance.
So back to the question I posed right
can we can we make up for for low low
statistical power with hard problems? Um
I think right so c certainly in some
cases you can but if you see this
inconsistency
you should be pretty suspicious right so
so I'm trying to illustrate say you have
a baseline model right where okay it's
correct on some questions and then you
have a strict if you had a strictly
better model
right that's better on more questions
then maybe okay maybe some of these
questions are really hard really
interesting and uh um and somehow I got
got them right. That that could be that
could mean a lot. Um but uh but the
reality seems more like the the third
line where maybe maybe you're a bit
better overall but uh um or about the
same overall but you get some questions
correctly uh some sometimes better
sometimes worse compared to the
baseline. So um so not always consistent
and I would maybe draw draw the the
analogy right like if someone can write
down pro if the right probably a very
hard and long proof of pp not equal to
np but some but they cannot define what
what np is or don't know some of the
basic concepts then maybe uh you suspect
okay maybe they they copied it somewhere
if it's truly open problems they cannot
copy somewhere but for for the problems
in the in the bench in the benchmarks
that that could be possible.
Um so that's the inconsistency.
Another thing we can look at is uh um
really what what is the probability that
a model gets a question correctly.
Right? So um so here is zooming in into
the same into the same kind of chart. Um
right so here we have we have this
question one 134 that only some very
good models get get consistently
correctly
right so slightly green here but uh but
we draw draw about a thousand samples
from for for each question and some of
the worst overall models
um still has a fairer chance of getting
them right right so in this case uh
that's the relevant number you have
still have 30% chance of get getting it
right. Uh some of the others are um
maybe less than 1% 10%.
Right? Depending on the case actually
once you have some chance of getting
getting the question correctly making a
more more reliable may not be that
impressive. Right? So so so one could
argue that actually the first percent is
very important. Right? So, so especially
if you have a verifiable question where
one way or another the verification is
easier maybe maybe a proof or something
then once you have a decent chance of
getting it correctly you can just try
try try again and verify and um with
with a little bit of help your model can
actually increase the the reliability
without doing too much actual impressive
Thanks.
Uh okay. So, so I think with um with
that bit of uh explor data analysis, I I
can convince you that at least for the
for the benchmarks that we have. Um
small the these small benchmarks are
still not not reliable even even if they
seem to contain some hard and very very
hardic problems.
Um
yeah. Um okay. And to to give a more
more to give an example from uh from day
life uh once my my kettle was broken uh
which is you use boil boil water and um
like I took took it apart asked the
model okay what what happened can you
can you help me identify what's what's
the problem? uh took a picture, ask what
it is. Oh, it says uh oh, there appears
to be a robot.
Um so
I I would uh trust it's later later
advice a lot less right and I think it
shows uh yeah well hard problems may
have many many steps and the probability
of error will increase exponentially as
the number of steps. So if you have some
constant prob probability of error then
it's very unlikely that you can solve
solve the hard problem. So there's some
some kind of a gradient is trying to say
here. Um although some sometimes you can
jump over it right you can still get the
answer correctly somehow.
uh but but you would trust it less.
Um and as a result so probably
statistical analysis uh is still
important now. Um and uh since since uh
we we uh we have have some uh some time
I I want to try try to convey uh the
basics of how how this works especially
maybe the the concept of s sampling from
from s superop sampling from a super
population. Um yeah in some sense this
is apparent from
basic stats in in textbooks but [snorts]
um this paper from Evan Miller
articulated pretty well in the context
of evaluations which I think will we
linked for for this class. Um so here I
I introduce a bit of notation on uh to
to make a uh to make the case of
sampling drawing multiple samples clear
later. So which is a bit different from
from his notation.
Um so first of all we have uh so X I is
a question X is the so so it's the I
question we have N total questions and
usually what an evaluation benchmark
does is it takes the um when when it
works on model A uh it takes all the
questions uh A ax returns say most
commonly a zero or two 01 value zero for
incorrect one for correct
and we get the the average uh a bar.
So um right and this is the particular
set of questions
but this uh uh estimation perspective
says well actually right this we can we
can draw we can draw other questions all
from the same distribution and these
questions is just the the particular
representative but we can't use it to
estimate the the variance of the real
population
Right? And and you can estimate with
those n samples and that's this variance
of uh a ax estimated by by the empirical
average on the samples.
Um yeah and then because uh because the
mean is computed by averaging and things
uh there's the concept of the the
standard standard error of the mean
which is quite um which is less than the
than the variance of the population by
by the factor of square or one over
square root.
it's give giving you a pretty clear
trend um multiply by by the uh you know
you can you can think of the variance a
as fairly constant because so so for
instance if 001 variables the maximum it
can be is one over four right and often
much smaller so so already you have an
upper bound on how big your your
standard error of the mean is without
having any without having any data
Um okay right but that just gives you if
you draw if you draw repeated samples um
if you draw other samples from the same
population what's the variance of the
mean um but actually what we we are more
interested in is comparing model A and
model B right and try to answer uh did
did my maybe model B do better than than
model Okay.
And and this this part is really for for
free, right? It's just better better
analysis. You already have you already
have all the data. So instead of asking
what's the variance of a you just ask
well what's the variance of uh a a ax
minus bx,
right? So, so if you have a set of
samples and there are zero one now, now
you have some some set it's either minus
one zero or one with some probability.
Um,
and this could potentially have a large
impact, right? So if A and B are per
almost perfectly correlated uh then then
by doing this paired as variance
estimation it could be reduced
potentially reduced to near to near
zero.
Um so
uh so yeah so that's a different version
of of v variance and once you have uh
which can also be normalized to be the
standard error and once you have the
standard error you compare it to to how
big uh how big the difference in mean is
to get the zcore right and uh and
according to to the theory the zcore
follows follows a standard normal
distribution so assuming your hand is
charges which which all of our
evaluations still satisfy. Um so for
instance being one uh one Z score away
is quite quite likely to happen just by
chance.
um by you know five five uh s uh right
so
yeah five I guess five standard errors
away is quite unlikely to happen and
very conventional standard is this about
two standard errors away which gives 5%
chance of happening by chance
okay um so that's uh that's how the
basic of this statistical and analysis
works and uh on this human human evol
data set we have 140 164 examples and uh
typically your your standard error will
be about 4% uh for for each for each
individual component. If you don't do if
you don't pair them up then uh then to
produce the point the 5% p value you
need about a 10% difference in
performance. Uh even with a paired test
you you typically still need about eight
8%. And these are larger than than
what's reported um by many papers.
Um so I yeah I can also give a bit of
intuition right. So if um if we are
considering unpaired as drawing from the
distribution so so suppose A scored 50%
on this year's exam but B scored 60% on
last year's exam they they contain
different exact questions but they are
drawn from the same distribution so so
that's unpaired in the paired version um
right so the in the unpaired version B
might have done better just because last
year was easier for instance but in a
paired In the parrot version, B also did
the same the exact same exam as A with
with exactly the same questions, right?
And then typically the 10% uh difference
seems more more significant,
right? So basically because because they
did they did the the exact same
problems, we can take advantage of it
even though if you met the higher
standard of of unpaired that that also
works.
Um so one interesting thing about LMS
that I work out here is um they they
have they can they can draw multiple
independent samples and especially with
a a agent reasoning models. This is
becoming more and more prominent.
Um yeah and humans certainly can't do
this. If I I solve the problem I cannot
forget it and reattempt.
So a common common confusion is actually
thinking that the only kind of noise
coming from these evoses or LM gives you
different predictions.
But but uh but according to this theory
if you if you're sensitive to what exact
questions are chosen uh that's also a
type of noise. In fact could be the more
important type of noise.
Um yeah, but we we can develop a system
to to to capture the setting as well
where where you have we all in in
addition to the question variable X we
also have the noise variable epsilon and
your your evaluations you you average
over both the questions and multiple
draws of the model
and yeah and you can you can estimate
the v variances as before and now now
actually there's a there's the
decomposition of of the total variance
into uh first the the the variance due
to due to choosing different questions
but averaging over the noise and and the
the the noise due to uh
due to due to sampling multiple times
from the model and actually it's a nice
nice identity that adds them adds them
up Um
right and you can you can you can as
before get the standard error versions
of of them uh and then apply the same
zcores
in in the in the now both paired and
with noise setting.
Um so I don't yeah don't need to do all
the details here but but I try to work
this out you know you correct to to make
sure they're correct and uh uh to test
it and run wrong a bunch of empirical
data so maybe others can can just use
the results without without fully
understanding that and do do it
themselves.
Um
yeah so even though uh you you have this
ability but sometimes it can lead to to
a bit of weirdness when when you when
you can say I I can do pro uh do this
question correctly with probability
eight a point eight.
Um so here we can have in in this
example we have eight questions model A
and model B. So model A um is overall
not that great. It has a 10% chance of
getting each question correctly. But
model B has a 100 100% chance of getting
the first four questions correctly or
zero chance of getting the the second
four correctly.
Um this can happen if you say do do RL
and maximize the expected reward. So
your expected reward increased but but
actually your uh the set of solvable
questions decreased.
um and it's not completely clear which
one is better even though the average
for on average B is much better
right so so but if uh if some of the
errors can be corrected say with a
verifier in the loop um then then a is
actually better
um yeah and and all of these can be uh
can be computed with a fairly simple
right variance mean variance and mean
estimations there. There's more
complexity with the correcting bias. But
one thing you don't have to do is you
don't you don't need to compute these
with bootstrap which is a perfectly fine
method. But uh but sometimes when the
answer is just like a p times one minus
p and uh they they say oh let's comput
this what bootstrap shows certain maybe
lack of thinking and we see a lot of
examples of people doing bootstrap
incorrectly in the in the literature.
Um yeah but actually the um another
reassuring thing is um multiple very
very wellestablished theories will give
uh roughly the same answer.
So namely bootstrap is another another
view point on this problem where you say
um mean right main idea is really uh if
you draw draw resamples
from the empirical distribution that's
the the samples that you are actually
given it's roughly behaves the same as
drawing drawing more samples from the
onene super population. Um yeah and if
you try to estimate that way you get
basically the same answer. Another quite
classic um math method is the sign test
treating treating this as testing an
hypothesis where the null hypothesis is
every where a and b is different each
have a 50% chance of being better
and the qu and it asks how likely is
this random model uh to to achieve an
result as as extreme as the one you
observed.
And this will also also get about the
same give you the same result as long as
a a and b uh performs about uh not not
too far away from each other.
Okay. So that that's the method. Um
right. So, so I think the the main um
contribution of this work uh is uh if I
if I try to to do this on all the all
the benchmarks all the model pair I have
um right carry out these different type
of analysis uh then maybe maybe the
numbers will be like fairly consistent
and you you don't need to con to say
well maybe my my model pairs is very is
very special and different from the
others.
So so that's what what I did uh from try
to do do this on all all all model pairs
and take the average of uh yeah take the
average of all the meaningful standard
errors both paired and unpaired.
Okay. And then then I can write this
down just for for each uh for each data
set.
Um and one immediate uh observation then
is that actually the par the paired test
tend to return um about the same about
the same result
as as the unpaired
which means one one so one way to
interpret it is okay maybe their their
correlation is about 50%.
Um right so if you actually apply the
unpaired uh uh method you you would have
to first multiply this by by square root
of two right resulting in less power.
But actually if you you do the paired um
you the standard error is about the
same. So
um yeah and and the on paired standard
error you can more or le you can more or
less just calculate from from the
accuracy on the data set.
So hopefully that that makes it a lot
easier. Um but but there is a slightly
weak dependence on the overall accuracy.
Right? So when when your when your
performance is near zero or one um there
there's a
the standard error is lower.
Yeah. But it's not a super strong
dependency
and uh yeah but if you you want to get
this little bit of additional accuracy.
I also gave uh uh the uh the estimated
standard error on each data set as a
function of its overall accuracy.
Right. So where we where are here the
the green curve the green dash line is
if is if I treat them all as independent
um and the blue one is is the prediction
by by another uh simple theory I will
talk about but first we can we can look
at a few few examples of these. So, so
for the most part once your your model
has a has a re reasonable performance on
this on this data set, it follows this
beta theory prediction. But uh but when
it's quite uh quite bad then uh then
maybe it's more like uh more like
independent
and this holds for for yeah for almost
all all the yeah all the data sets and I
see it very uh yeah except with a few
possible deviations
right one is here it's mou it's a
multiple choice test so so when all the
models are really really bad right like
even your random model can can get the
one over five or one over four. Uh so so
there it was more like independent but
once the model gets better it follows
the the predict the beta prediction
similar for live code bunch.
Um h and also also quite some uh yeah
and you also got the same result for for
sweet bunch with now with more more data
points giving more confidence. Um and
there's one just one pair of outliers
that that I saw and I digged into it a
little bit and there were is three uh
three fixer versus three fixer with a
filter result.
Um yeah where you you got a strict
improvement and that's much less
standard error.
Um I think yeah it's a bit reassuring to
say okay this this is not some real
universal phenomenon. I really only only
applies if you are testing OMS.
Um right. So even though uh these these
are a diverse set somewhat yeah some for
somewhat diverse set of LMS are trained
by different people on different data um
yeah but using different agent as well
but they are they are still all all and
uh seems does seem to have similar noise
behavior.
Um
okay so now I try to explain this a
little. So why why is it that uh uh it
we got noise at that level? So one thing
we can do is look at the empirical
distribution of uh of the probability
uh of getting correct for uh for each
for each tier of models from from really
bad models to the best models.
So here uh this is the the cumulative
distribution function. Okay. And see
what what do they look like? And it
turns out you can you can fit a beta
distribution after accounting for the
true real zeros. the questions where no
model solved
and uh and on once um once your
performance is uh good enough
uh the the biodess
let's say of the beta distribution
increases often time often with roughly
the parameters summing summing to one
and that that corresponds to the to the
prediction that we showed before.
Okay. So, so again right like if you you
use this model then you can predict how
how much noise there is without having
all the individual results. Um yeah and
beta distribution is this uh um
distribution on the interval 0 to one
where in in this uh in this range with I
guess uh parameter summing to one they
are they are biodal
whereas for for parameter summing to be
something bigger it's more more un
um okay so this this also appears to to
fit u multiple for multiple data sets
here. MLU pro uh channel thought um and
and more discrete um predictions like on
SW bench verified as well
because now now the empirical
predictions are stepwise because there
there's only only so many models where
we don't have multiple predictions but
but the overall trend um still seems to
fit well.
Okay. Um, so
that's uh that's what I wanted to say
about measuring noise. There are other
other works such as run with more
multiple seeds or something like
measuring the variance of your training
curve which actually tend to lead to an
underestimation.
So after after doing doing both the
exploratory data analysis and some uh
summary of it right we can we can in
fact recommend this right in increasing
accuracy right so if you really just
want a ball of ballpark figure and just
look at the table right it tells you
what what the standard error is uh by by
data set and you don't don't need to to
do to do the additional work to get a
little bit more accuracy you can you can
look at uh uh you know the these these
charts find okay what's the range of
your your your uh model
uh then read read off that chart right
uh yeah you can um you can also
uh provide pro provide your your results
on each um uh each question and use my
code right then and then runs all
together gives your your particular
comparisons in the context of all the
all all the other comparisons. So if you
if you you're getting some something
strange, you immediately know. Yeah, but
you you can also do do your own own
tests and calculations. But uh it seems
fairly uh errorprone because there are
several different types.
Um right. So no noise is the the thing
that I think I took the f furthest here.
But there are um a few other things you
could do with this kind of data tool. Um
I think one kind of interesting one is
you can say look at uh um
see this works.
Yeah, you can look look at examples and
see um well uh is is this example
correlated with a model negatively
correlated with the overall model
performance? So you you know you the
better the model is the worse it does on
on this example and we can find some
some such examples in in many of the
data sets uh right but a lot of them are
not not actual errors except on this
on this MVP
um where where you have a bunch of
negatively correlated examples that are
actually either inconsistent or somehow
or
being incorrect.
Um yeah but but not not all all of them
are mistakes. So so this gives one way
to audit uh the quality of the
evaluation set. Um yeah find a few few
mistakes in MBPP and which got
incorporated into MBPP plus. Uh you can
you can also try to find suspicious
models actually right. So, so once you
say you have some some suspect examples
where where are the leading model that
that say wasn't wasn't cheating um
we will kind of overlook what's in the
evaluation data set but there there may
be a few model which gives the the exact
answer from the evaluation data set on
on this wrong example. So if there are a
few of those you can gather some
evidence on what what models may may may
maybe have trend on the evaluation data.
Um, okay.
Yeah, I think this is more for bench
benchmark builder, right? So, that's the
that was the absolute level of noise.
Um,
but an important question is really how
uh what what kind of of effect size can
you measure with with your benchmark,
right? So, this also depends on the on
the standard error. But uh but on many
uh many models when they release they
release a ser series of models from
small to large right. So a place for to
get signal is now when say when you
doubled your model size how much
improvements you get right scaling law
which gives a consistency improvement
and you can ask okay so how on on your
on the on each benchmark how much signal
to noise ratio uh really also also me
measured by zcore is there
um and and here you have
still mostly probably just
mostly a function of the size still but
uh but occasional
uh differences right so so MLU can very
reliably distinguish the next larger
model whereas many of the code code
evaluations like human evol cannot even
distinguish doubling the model
Um
yeah, I think
wrong time. Um
a few examples, but okay, but I think we
can
uh and here. So I give a way to look at
all the question results. uh uh spend
more most of the effort characterizing
how big the noise is but also show a few
few ways to get some other information.